Guide to the Oregon Hops and Brewing Archives Oral History Collection 2014-2017
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections and Archives Research Center
Oregon Hops and Brewing Archives Oral History Collection
2014-2017
Edmunson-Morton, Tiah K.
OH 035
259.00 gigabytes, including 70 sets of video and audio files
Special Collections and Archives Research Center 121 The Valley Library Oregon State University Corvallis, OR, 97331-4501 Phone: 541-737-2075 Email: scarc@oregonstate.edu Web: http://scarc.library.oregonstate.edu/findingaids
The Oregon Hops and Brewing Archives Oral History Collection is a growing repository of interviews with industry professionals, journalists and community members. More specifically, this collection documents the stories of people involved with Pacific Northwest hops and barley farming; craft and home brewing, cider, and mead; and scientific research. All interviews are available for streaming online.
Biographical Note:
Lisa Allen is a brewer at Heater Allen Brewing in McMinnville. Allen was born in Portland and grew up in Tualatin, Oregon, but spent her junior year in Moraga, California. Allen was strong academically in science and math, but was also interested in history and English. She started at Oregon State University in 2001, studying Anthropology/Archaeology. After she graduated she lived in New Zealand for six months, where she worked in the restaurant industry. After returning to the U.S., Allen got a summer job at Pelican Brewing; she helped open the Monroe McMenamins in Corvallis in 2006. Allen also worked in the wine industry, starting with harvest and then working in tasting rooms, while simultaneously studying for the GRE and applying for grad school in historic preservation. She was accepted into a graduate program in England for historic preservation, but by then had decided to pursue a career in wine. In 2009, Allen left the wine industry to join her father at Heater Allen Brewing, which he'd opened in 2007 after a long career as an investment banker.
Rick Allen is the owner and head brewer at Heater Allen in McMinnville, Oregon. He was born in Palo Alto, California and lived there for most of his childhood. He graduated from Woodside High School and though he was interested in a variety of subjects, including chemistry and meteorology, he chose to study business at Oregon State University. He was a member of Beta Theta Pi fraternity. The Allen family has a deep connection to Oregon State University: Allen's grandfather went to OAC (Class of 1923) and his grandmother studied Home Economics; his parents both attended OSU, meeting during their freshman year at an "alternative Thanksgiving" retreat and marrying during their junior year; his two brothers attended OSU; he met his wife at OSU; and their daughter, Lisa, attended in the early 2000s. After university, Allen took a position as an investment banker in Portland, with short moves to Washington and California for employment; he left that field in the early 2000s. An avid home brewer, Allen considered a second career as a vintner, but decided to open a brewery in 2007 in McMinnville, Oregon.
Kyle Almlie is a home brewer and graduate teaching assistant in the chemistry department of Oregon State University. He grew up in Chico, California, where he stayed through college graduation from California State University-Chico with a B.S. in Chemistry in 2012. He moved to Oregon State University that same year to study Analytical Chemistry and work as a Graduate Teaching Assistant.
Warren Aney is alum of Oregon State University, who received his Master’s degree in the 1970s. He went on to work as a wildlife ecologist, and later worked for a Portland-based travel agency leading wine tours. Aney met vintner and brewer Charles Coury, who started Oregon's first post-Prohibition microbrewery in 1980, through their mutual interest in wine.
John Annen is a fourth generation hop grower in Mount Angel. Annen’s family came to the area in the late 19th century from Wisconsin and Minnesota, following the priests and sisters who moved to Oregon when the Catholic Abbey was established. He comes from a large family, with ten siblings and an extended family with lots of cousins; most of his siblings stayed in farming, but Annen was left alone to run the farm in the mid 1990s. He has two sons, and one has taken over the management of the farm.
Natalie Baldwin is the Head Brewer at Burnside Brewing. She grew up near Vail, Colorado, where her dad was a ski instructor. While she was growing up she spent a lot of time outdoors, skiing and mountain biking; she was also interested in art and photography, but by the end of high school decided to pursue education in Biological Chemistry at University of Colorado in Denver. She moved to Portland in 2012 and started working at Pints Brewing Company in 2013; she stayed there through 2015, when she left to take a position at Burnside Brewing.
Fred Bowman co-founded Portland Brewing Company in 1986. Bowman was born in San Francisco; moved to Montana; to Empire, Oregon in elementary school; and finally settled in Hillsboro, where he has spent most of his life. Bowman's first job was for worked for a Volkswagen distributor in high school, which fit with his interest in cars and mechanics. In addition to cars, Bowman was also interested in biology and music, playing trumpet in the youth symphony. He travelled through Europe after graduating from High School, sparking another lifelong interest in beer and brewing. He returned in time to start school at Oregon State University, but soon transferred to University of Oregon and then again to Portland State University. He returned to his job with Volkswagen, a position he held for 16 more years. He began home brewing in the late 1970s and after leaving Volkswagen Bowman, Art Larrance, and Jim Goodwin joined forces to open a brewery. They hired Bert Grant (Yakima Brewing) as a consultant, which resulted in a licensing agreement for them to brew Grant's beer in Portland; this ended in the early 1990s. Bowman and other early microbrewers were instrumental in the passage of Oregon's Brewpub Bill in 1985, which allowed breweries to brew and sell beer onsite. By 1998 the company was in financial trouble, and it was sold in 2004. Bowman had been employed as a brewing consultant, work he continued to do after the brewery was sold.
Brad Clack is a retired hop buyer for S.S. Steiner (now Hopsteiner). Clack's family did farm work on the Oregon coast before moving to Salem, where Clack has spent most of his life. He started working in the hop industry in 1978 and has deep relationships with growers and hops brokers. He retired in 2015, and his son has taken over his duties at S.S. Steiner.
Jeff Clawson has worked for the Department of Food Science and Technology as the research brewery and food processing manager since 1993. Clawson grew up in Davis, California, where his father was a University of California Extension Agent and his mom worked as a department administrative assistant. He moved to Oregon to study Agribusiness at Eastern Oregon College (now Eastern Oregon University) in La Grande. It was in college that Clawson took a class in brewing, which became a personal hobby and ultimately led to a career. He transferred to Oregon State University to finish his B.S., adding a Food Science minor and working with Mina McDaniel on sensory analysis. After graduating in 1988 he worked at NORPAC Foods in Stayton, Oregon. He returned to OSU for graduate school in 1991 to study Rangeland Resources and Water Quality; he finished in 1993, and took a position with the Department of Food Science and Technology.
Bill Coleman is part of a large multigenerational hop growing family, primarily based in St. Paul and Mt. Angel. He was born and raised in the area and all the children worked on the farm; many of the family members are still actively involved in Coleman Agriculture. The Coleman farms experienced rapid expansion from the 1950s through the 1970s, and as a result branches of the family began to become more specialized in the work they do; Bill Coleman has always been interested in and excelled at mechanics, and he developed new pieces of equipment and processes that have made the farm and the industry more efficient. In addition to the work on the farm and involvement in the church community, Coleman has also travelled extensively.
John Coleman is a hop grower based in St. Paul, Oregon. He manages the hops and perennial crops for Coleman Ag, a large family run company. Coleman grew up in St. Paul and spent most of his extra time working on the farm. He went to St. Paul Parochial and attended St. Paul High School, where he was active in the Future Farmers of America. He attended Oregon State University, where he was in the Lambda Chi Alpha fraternity and studied Political Science; he graduated in 1988. He has held various positions in the family business, but is currently the Perennial Crops Manager.
Denny Conn is a home brewer, author, and podcaster. Conn was born in Newton, Iowa, where his father and grandfather ran a lumberyard; Conn worked there as a child. Conn played guitar in rock bands, performed in bars and talent shows as a kid. He graduated from high school in 1980 and attended Iowa State University. He initially wanted to be a chemistry teacher, but later decided he wanted to be an English teacher. He dropped out of college part way through because he wanted to play in rock bands. He moved to Eugene, Oregon, where he attended Lane Community College for electronic technician coursework. He got a job helping a friend’s digital audio technology company, and they toured with Split Ends, Supertramp, and Tom Petty and the Heartbreakers. When he returned, he worked at a video store, the Hult Center, and opened a recording studio. His wife bought him a Pike Place Brewing home brewing kit from Costco in 1998; brewing made sense to him because of his chemistry education, his love of cooking, and his experimental nature. He learned about different styles and methods, and soon began to experiment in a rather radical way. One method was batch sparging, which turned out to be a divisive one for home brewers; Conn started publishing his information about batch sparging online in 2003 to 2004, and people criticized it. He also experimented with ingredients, including rye for a Rye IPA, which John Maier from Rogue liked; Conn’s RIPA as inspiration for one of Rogue’s anniversary beers. He's also experimented with equipment, and is a big fan of the Pico-Brew. He and his friend Drew Beechum have co-written the books Experimental Brewing and Homebrew All-stars; they also have a podcast, Experimental Homebrewing.
Ted Cox was born in Eugene, Oregon, but soon moved to California to help his aunt manage her ranch. He graduated from Chaffey Junior College in 1967 and from La Verne College with a B.A. in Physical Education in 1969. He did two tours with the Peace Corps (1969-1973) in Sierra Leone and Belize. In Sierra Leone he worked in a teacher's college and in Belize he coached track and field, helping to create a physical fitness manual that is still used today. He returned to Oregon in 1973 to attend graduate school at Oregon State University, graduating with his master's in Physical Education in 1976; his thesis was entitled "Physical fitness parameters of male youth in USA and Belize, Central America." He was also the women's volleyball coach and taught both physical education and first aid at Linn Benton Community College (1975-1976). He opened the Old World Deli in 1977 and soon bought the building, which houses shops and the Oregon Trail Brewery (established 1987). He is the author of three books: When British Honduras became Belize: A Peace Corps memoir, Murray Loop: Journey of an Oregon Family, and The Toledo Incident of 1925: Three days that made history in Toledo, Oregon.
Chris Crabb is the Public Relations Director of the Oregon Brewers Festival and owner of the firm Crabbsoup Public Relations. She grew up in Beaverton, Oregon and attended Sunset High School. In 1991 she graduated from the University of Oregon with a BA in Journalism, with an emphasis on Public Relations. She was the PR Director and Account Manager for Campbell Production/Consulting Group, and has been working as a PR Associate at Weinstein PR since 2009. In 2003, she started her own firm Crabbsoup. Her career has focused on the hospitality field, with an emphasis on food and beverage events and promotion. She's worked with the Oregon Brewers Festival, Holiday Ale Festival, and BrewFest in the Park, as well as many other individual brewery clients.
Blake Crosby is a 5th generation hop grower who grew up on his family's farm in Woodburn, Oregon. Crosby attended the University of Oregon, where he earned a B.A. in History in 2008, and Willamette University, where he earned an M.B.A. in 2013. He is the CEO and President of Crosby Hop Farm.
Brian Crosby is a fourth generation hop family member and works at Crosby Hop Farm LLC as an accounts manager. Crosby was born in Portland, Oregon and grew up on the family farm in Woodburn. Hops production was a community and family effort, and he and his siblings all worked on the farm. After graduation, Crosby left Woodburn and joined the Navy; after three years he left the military and went to Oregon State University to study Civil Engineering; while there he also played rugby. He worked for a construction company in Portland, moved to Bend to run their local office, left the industry during the 2008 recession, and spent the next several years working in construction and earning a degree in Financial Planning. He returned to the farm in the late 2000s as a financial manager and salesperson.
William Dettwyler is the owner of Codus Medicus, Inc. He grew up on a hop farm in Silverton, Oregon, where he worked on his family farm and processing facilities in the 1930s through the 1950s, when they sold the farm. He graduated from the Oregon Institute of Technology with an Associate of Science degree in Clinical Laboratory Science/Medical Technology/Technologist in 1958. He has done lab work for since the early 1950s, and has owned Codus Medicus since 1961; his work has allowed him to travel extensively through the U.S.
Otto Fredrick “Fred” Eckhardt (1926-2015) was a well-known advocate, critic, educator, mentor, and historian. Born in Everett, Washington, Eckhardt traveled widely with the U.S. Marine Corps before moving to Portland, Oregon. After leaving careers as a swim instructor and studio photographer, Eckhardt began photographing new Northwest pubs and writing about beer full time for various brewing publications. Eckhardt rose to prominence in the brewing community with his 1970 A Treatise on Lager Beers, a guide to homebrewing and the evolution of lager beer (a hobby which was notably still illegal at the time of publication). His 1989 The Essentials of Beer Style is still considered a required read for brewers and beer lovers alike. A beloved member of the brewing community, Eckhardt has been called the icon, pioneer, and founding father of craft beer, as well as the much beloved “Dean of American beer writing.”
Jeff Edgerton is the Brewmaster at BridgePort Brewing Company in Portland, Oregon. Edgerton grew up in Canby, where he was surrounded by agriculture and hop yards. After graduating from Canby High School, Edgerton moved to Corvallis to attend Oregon State University, where he majored in Microbiology; he graduated in 1987. After leaving OSU he took a job at the Blitz-Weinhard brewery, working here as a Lab Tech, Quality Assurance Manager, and Brewery Microbiologist from 1989 to 1998; the brewery closed in 1999. In 1998, Edgerton became the Quality Assurance Manager at BridgePort Brewing, six years later he became Assistant Brewmaster, and then in 2010 became the Brewmaster.
Emily Engdahl is the Executive Director of The Pink Boots Society. She grew up in Portland, Oregon, where she was surrounded by family, art, culture, food, and gardens. After graduating from Grant High School in 1994 she went to Southern Oregon University for a year, but didn't continue her studies there. She returned to Portland in the late 1990s, and in 2000 started working at Professional Fiduciary Services providing social service coordination for mentally ill or elderly clients. In 2003, she graduated from Marylhurst University with a degree in Communications and a certificate in Conflict Resolution. She began home brewing in 2010 or 2011, and fermentation soon became core to her work. In addition to working as a freelance graphic designer, Engdahl was the co-founder of #pdxbeergeeks, a community-based beer blog, worked as an event development coordinator for Women Enjoying Beer, was a beer blogger for "1859: Oregon's Magazine," and was the creator and owner of Oregon Beer Country. In 2013, she became the Executive Director of the Pink Boots Society.
Teri Fahrender grew up in a German-American family in Wisconsin. She has a B.A. in Business Administration from the University of Wisconsin, Eau Claire and earned a certificate in Brewing Technology from the Siebel Institute of Technology in Chicago. She worked as the Brewmaster at Berkeley's Golden Gate Brewing Company in 1989 before becoming the Head Brewer at Triple Rock Brewing Company (1989-1990). She moved to Eugene to become the Brewmaster at the Steelhead Brewing Company (1990-2007) and worked as a brewing consultant before becoming a Territory Sales Manager for Country Malt/Great Western Malting (2009-2015). In September 2015, she became the Malt Innovation Center Manager at Great Western Malting. She founded the Pink Boots Society in 2007, which is a non-profit organization dedicated to education and support of women in the brewing industries.
Irene Firmat is the founder and CEO of Full Sail Brewing Company, located in Hood River, Oregon. She was born in Havana, Cuba and moved to New York when she was 3. She moved to Oregon in the early 1980s for a job as a buyer for the department store Meier and Frank. After several years she decided to change careers; inspired by the food and drink culture that was emerging in the Northwest, she found partners to start a brewpub in Hood River in 1987, aptly called Hood River Brewing Co. David Logsdon, who later founded the yeast company Wyeast and Logsdon Farmhouse Ales, was their original brewer. Soon Logsdon left and brewer Jamie Emmerson replaced him. Emmerson and Firmat soon married, living in Portland and commuting to Hood River. Full Sail became employee-owned in 1999; in 2015, the employees voted to sell to Oregon Craft Brewers Co., a local investment group.
Gary Fish is the founder and board president of Deschutes Brewery. He was born and raised in Northern California, where his father was a wine grape grower and a part of the state's modern wine renaissance. He moved to Utah to attend University of Utah, working his way through college waiting tables; he stayed to work in the restaurant industry. He and his wife returned to the West Coast in the late 1980s, settling in Bend with the goal of opening a brewpub after his parents had travelled through the city returning from a college class reunion at Oregon State University. Deschutes Brewery opened in 1988, with Fish running the restaurant and John Harris as the first brewer; the first years were rocky, the company soon saw success and expanded. In 2008, they opened a brewpub in Portland and in 2016 announced plans to build a new plant in Roanoke, North Carolina. Fish built a company with community values in mind, and has been recognized as a civic leader in Central Oregon and beyond; in 2012 he was awarded the Civic Leadership Award and the Governors Gold Awards. Fish has also been quite involved in the brewery profession too; from 2014 to 2016 he was the Chairman of the Brewers Association. Fish stepped down as President and CEO in 2017, but he's staying on as the Founder and Board Member.
Mick Flanagan is a mechanic at BridgePort Brewing Company. He was born in Sydney, Australia and spent his childhood living there and in the United States. He graduated from high school in Portland in 1987 and has worked for the brewery since 1989.
John Foyston is a beer culture freelance journalist in Portland, Oregon. He was born in a small town in East British Columbia; his family moved to Vancouver before settling in Portland in 1956. He attended Sunset High School and then studied Liberal Arts at the University of Oregon. He had a variety of jobs (mechanic, musician) before becoming an Oregonian Staff writer in 1994, a position he left in 2015 to pursue freelance work full time.
Dana Garves is a brewing chemist who owns and operates BrewLab, a company that provides chemical analyses for breweries, cideries, meaderies, and home brewers. Garves has always been interested in chemistry, starting with early successes in science and math classes in the Seattle area. She joined the Science Olympiad team in high school, serving as the club president her junior and senior years, and was enrolled in the International Baccalaureate program. She also played competitive softball through the end of high school, and was active in community service and volunteering. She began coursework at the University of Oregon with a goal of being a high school chemistry teacher, and helped out with a UO STEM summer camps for girls. She graduated with a degree in Environmental Chemistry in 2010. That same year she saw a Craigslist ad that Ninkasi Brewing was looking for a chemist. During her employment she was a Lab Tech who propagated their in-house yeast, ran the quality control program, and collaborated with Team Hybriddyne to launch Ninkasi yeast into space. She left Ninkasi in 2014 to set up BrewLab.
Cheryl Gillson is the Rogue Farms marketing and farm manager in Independence, Oregon. Gillson was born in California, but moved to Oregon when she was 18 months old; her family settled near Hillsboro, where Gillson had opportunities to grow her interests in outdoor activities and photography. She moved to San Francisco in the early 2000s and moved back to Oregon in 2004, which is when she got her first position at Rogue Ales and Spirits working as founder Jack Joyce's assistant. That position led her back to San Francisco for a few years, but she left the company to move to Istanbul, Turkey in 2010 with general plans to explore and travel. After four years in Turkey she returned to Oregon and to Rogue. After a few months of odd jobs for the company she was transferred to her position on the Rogue Farms.
Gayle Goschie is a third-generation hop grower and Vice President for Hops and Winegrapes at her family's Goschie Farms, Inc. in Silverton, Oregon. Gosche studied at both University of Oregon and Portland State University, earning a degree in Political Science at PSU. After college she worked for a small advertising agency in Portland, returning to the family farm in 1981.
John Harris is the owner of Ecliptic Brewing in Portland, Oregon. Harris grew up in Beaverton, developing an early interest in astronomy and home brewing. He was one of the first brewers at McMenamins, answering an ad in Willamette Week they'd posted for a brewer in Hillsdale; he worked there from 1986 to 1988. He left to take a job at Deschutes Brewing, where he was the founding Brewmaster for the brewery, which had opened in 1987; he stayed with that position until 1992, when he moved to Portland. That move led to a position at Full Sail Brewery, working in their small experimental brewery on the waterfront and focusing on the brewmaster reserve line. In 2012 he left Full Sail, and in 2013 he opened his own brewery.